Guide to the New York City Immigrant Labor History Project Oral History Collection OH.014
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
- New York City Immigrant Labor History Project
  - Weinstein, Helen Taub: Transcript, 1974 May 1 (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - Williams, Ellen, 1975 October 23, November 12, and December 3 (Box 25, Cassette 223, 223A & 223B, Box 14)
    Ellen Williams was born on April 30, 1938 in Darliston, Jamaica. She was one of nine children. Her father was a coachman and a farmer and her mother managed the household. Williams attended school in Jamaica up to the sixth standard in the British education system. She immigrated to the United States on June 17, 1947 and lived with her cousin at 68 West 117th Street in the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. She married in 1948 and lived on 120th Street in Harlem. She later moved to Morningside Avenue in the Morningside Heights neighborhood of Manhattan and to the Bronx, where she resided at the time of the interview. She worked as a baby nurse for various families in New York City and as a nurse's aide in the Jewish Home and Hospital for the Aged in the Upper West Side neighborhood of Manhattan. She joined Local 1199 Drug, Hospital, and Health Care Employees Union in 1963 or 1964. She was a member of the West Indian and American Friendly Society and St. John’s Lodge in New York City.
    This interview was conducted by Sasha Silverstein at the offices of Local 1199 Drug, Hospital, and Health Care Employees Union in Manhattan, New York on October 23, November 12, and December 3, 1975. This interview covers Ellen Williams’ childhood in Darliston, Jamaica; her immigration to the United States (US); and her life and work as a baby nurse and a nurses' aide in New York, New York. Williams begins by describing her childhood in Jamaica, specifically recalling her father’s occupation as a coachman in Kingston; the perception of this job as prestigious due to the wages and uniforms; and his occupation later as a pimento and coffee farmer in Darliston. She recalls that despite the racial segregation in the schools and churches, children were generally friendly with one another. She describes working as a baby nurse for a family in Jamaica, noting that they treated her like family; deferred to her on matters regarding their children; and introduced her to politicians and other friends of theirs. She discusses the differences between life in the city and in the country; the different roles of men and women in both the household and society; the finances of her household; Catholic traditions, including holiday services and the role of godparents; and other secular traditions, particularly birthdays and festivals.
    Williams explains that she immigrated to the US at the behest of her cousin and recalls the sponsorship and monetary requirements for her immigration in June 1947. Her initial impression of New York City was that it was filled with trees and well-dressed people. She explains that while her cousins helped her to acclimate to life in New York, she had difficulty adapting to the winter weather. She describes working as a baby nurse for various families in New York City, recalling that after her marriage in 1948, she only took jobs that did not require her to live with her employers. She describes her work and training as a nurse’s aide at the Jewish Home and Hospital for the Aged in the Upper West Side neighborhood of Manhattan. Williams recalls joining Local 1199 Drug, Hospital, and Health Care Employees Union in 1963 or 1964 and notes that despite her initial skepticism of its benefits, the union gave hospital workers greater job security and wage increases. Other topics include the differences between her work as a baby nurse and nurse's aide; her siblings’ education, careers, and families; her husband’s occupation and family; her interactions with and impressions of union leaders, particularly Doris Turner and Leon Davis; her involvement in the West Indian and American Friendly Society and St. John’s Lodge; and her visits to Jamaica to see her family.
    Local 1199 Drug, Hospital, and Health Care Employees Union (New York, N.Y.).; Jamaicans |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews.
  - Untitled, Undated
  - Untitled, Undated
  - Untitled, Undated
  - Untitled, Undated
  - Untitled, Undated
  - Untitled, Undated
  - Untitled, Undated
  - Untitled, Undated
  - Untitled, Undated
  - Untitled, Undated
  - Untitled, Undated
  - Untitled, Undated
  - Untitled, Undated
  - Untitled, Undated
  - Untitled, Undated
  - Untitled, Undated
  - Untitled, Undated
  - Untitled, Undated
  - Untitled, Undated
  - Untitled, Undated
  - Untitled, Undated
  - Untitled, Undated
  - Untitled, Undated